<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: travel | Chris Stevens]]></title>
  <link href="http://chrisstevens.us/blog/categories/travel/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://chrisstevens.us/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-31T10:04:53-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://chrisstevens.us/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Chris Stevens]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[By The Numbers: College Station for $53]]></title>
    <link href="http://chrisstevens.us/blog/2011/10/18/by-the-numbers-college-station-for-53-dollars/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-18T16:14:02-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://chrisstevens.us/blog/2011/10/18/by-the-numbers-college-station-for-53-dollars</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.chrisstevens.us/images/charlotte-flying.jpg"><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.chrisstevens.us/images/charlotte-flying-225x300.jpg" title="[Charlotte Flying]" ></a></p>

<p>&ldquo;By the numbers&rdquo; in aviation essentially means operating the aircraft in a manner intended by the manufacturer and validated via flight test.  We have numbers for takeoff power, approach speed, engine rpm, fuel flow, etc.  Most of these are spelled out in the airplane flight manual and hopefully ensure safe and performant operations.</p>

<p>This post is more about the trip itself and addresses a question (or class of questions) that I feel like I answer frequently.  If it works out, it may turn into a series.</p>

<h2>How much does it cost to fly to &hellip;?</h2>

<p>This question, along with &ldquo;how long&rdquo; and &ldquo;how much [stuff|people]&rdquo; can be combined to formulate a total value of a trip or experience, so I&rsquo;ll give you our specs on a specific trip that we make very frequently via road and air.  My time is valuable whether used for work, family, or rest, so it always weighs heavily in our personal value proposition.  Yours might be different.</p>

<p>We are going to gloss over acquisition, maintenance, and other fixed (or nearly fixed) costs of both the aircraft and the car and just focus on this one trip.  It doesn&rsquo;t matter whether the car sits in the garage or the airplane sits in the hanger, it costs what it costs and the value scales from there.</p>

<h2>Flower Mound to College Station</h2>

<p>Drive
Fly</p>

<p>Time</p>

<ul>
<li><p>8 hours round-trip (average)</p></li>
<li><p>This is for average traffic and approx 30 minutes stop time each way to feed the baby.</p></li>
<li><p>3 hours round-trip (average)</p></li>
<li><p>We can do this reliably even during DFW rush-hour and most Texas weather.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Cost</p>

<ul>
<li><p>$85.64</p></li>
<li><p>416 miles round-trip, $3.50/gal at 17mpg for our Acura MDX</p></li>
<li><p>$138.00</p></li>
<li><p>3 hours, $4.60/gal at 10gal/hr</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Pros</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Air-conditioning.</p></li>
<li><p>All-weather (basically).</p></li>
<li><p>Ability to stop more easily (esp. with kids).</p></li>
<li><p>Rush-hour agnostic.</p></li>
<li><p>Less fatigue upon arrival.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Cons</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Total duration is brutal.</p></li>
<li><p>Leaving the DFW metro area can be brutal.</p></li>
<li><p>Weather can be an issue.</p></li>
<li><p>Lack of air conditioning during the summer.</p></li>
<li><p>Pre-flight adds about 15 minutes to each leg.</p></li>
<li><p>Carseat install/de-install is a pain.</p></li>
</ul>


<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>I typically feel quite a bit better at the end of each flying leg versus a driving leg.  Part of the driving fatigue is related to total duration, but I&rsquo;d argue that most flights are less taxing overall than the same trip on the road.</p>

<p>For an extra $53 on average, I save about 5 hours of travel time for the weekend.  Whether I end up working those saved hours or relaxing with the family, those are my hours and not wasted on the road.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Five Reasons why your Traxo Travel Score Matters]]></title>
    <link href="http://chrisstevens.us/blog/2011/06/20/five-reasons-why-your-traxo-travel-score-matters/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-20T03:00:15-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://chrisstevens.us/blog/2011/06/20/five-reasons-why-your-traxo-travel-score-matters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.chrisstevens.us/images/travel-score-tiers.jpg"><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.chrisstevens.us/images/travel-score-tiers.jpg" title="[Travel Score Tiers]" ></a></p>

<p>Even if you&rsquo;re not a Double Black Diamond Executive Platinum High-Fivin' the TSA kind of traveler, you probably take several trips each year for business and leisure.  You do take vacations right?  I hope you do.</p>

<p>If you are a <a href="http://www.traxo.com">Traxo</a> member, you can turn those trips into some cool stuff and it is launching today as the &ldquo;Traxo Travel Score&rdquo;.  I usually leave the PR to the company, but I think this feature is particularly cool and can provide some great value to all kinds of travelers.</p>

<p>Similar to how <a href="http://www.klout.com">Klout</a> measures your online influence, Traxo can use all of your previous trip data to calculate your travel score.  Your score is a measure of your overall travel experience.</p>

<h3>5 Reasons Why Your Traxo Travel Score Matters</h3>

<ol>
<li><p> Better travel recommendations.  Ask your Traxo Buddies with the highest scores or another high-scoring member.</p></li>
<li><p> Build your travel reputation.  If you write about travel, we hope your score will be one of your best credentials.</p></li>
<li><p> Earn perks.  Watch for great rewards from our partners.</p></li>
<li><p> Get better service.  Travel vendors are excited to recognize expert travelers.</p></li>
<li><p> Compete with your friends.  Who doesn&rsquo;t like a good competition.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>When I was first introduced to Klout, I had a hard time identifying the real-world value proposition.  In their defense, they were pretty new at the time and may have been a bit stealthy in their positioning.  The real-world value definitely there, though.  If you are influential online and speak out about a product or service either postively or negatively, online or in-person, an astute business owner can see a measure of your influence and has incentive to give you better service.  Well, in theory, at least.</p>

<p>Your travel score will work the same way.  As you visit states and countries, spend nights away from home, and cover more miles, our system will find those trips and give you credit for those.  As, your score (your travel reputation) goes up, we hope you&rsquo;ll receive benefits from our partners and travel suppliers based on how, when, and where you travel.  Also, if you link your favorite travel accounts (airlines, hotels, car companies), we will give you <strong>more</strong> points because those bookings can be verified through our platform!</p>

<p>Finally, if you&rsquo;re thinking that you don&rsquo;t travel enough or always drive yourself, never fear!  It just so happens that my family fits nicely into that category as well, except that we avoid commercial airlines and fly ourselves.  Be sure to link your travel accounts because Traxo will always be looking at those for new activity.  But did you know that you can check-in with <a href="http://www.gowalla.com">Gowalla</a> on your smartphone during your trip and we count those check-ins as verified travel just like an airline or hotel booking.  More on that in a later <a href="http://chrisstevens.us/2011/06/fun-with-gowalla">post</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
