<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Mooney | Chris Stevens]]></title>
  <link href="http://chrisstevens.us/blog/categories/mooney/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://chrisstevens.us/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-14T09:49:59-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://chrisstevens.us/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Chris Stevens]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annual Maintenance - Part Two]]></title>
    <link href="http://chrisstevens.us/blog/2011/06/28/annual-maintenance-part-two/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-28T13:40:16-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://chrisstevens.us/blog/2011/06/28/annual-maintenance-part-two</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.chrisstevens.us/images/mooney-annual-2010.jpg"><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.chrisstevens.us/images/mooney-annual-2010.jpg" title="[Mooney Annual &ndash; 2010]" ></a></p>

<p>The great news is that our little 45-year old airplane had no major issues this year.  We had both mechanical and avionics inspections going simultaneously and bought 1 battery, 1 ELT (emergency locator transmitter), and 1 very tired transponder (responds to ATC radar) in the process.</p>

<p>The subsequent test flight was uneventful, although those are always a bit nerve wracking.  Let&rsquo;s just say that I know where a good grassy field is just south of the Northwest Regional Airport runway.</p>

<p>It looks like we&rsquo;re ready for football season.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annual Maintenance - Part One]]></title>
    <link href="http://chrisstevens.us/blog/2011/06/13/annual-maintenance-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-13T05:46:04-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://chrisstevens.us/blog/2011/06/13/annual-maintenance-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.chrisstevens.us/images/mooney-prop-vertical-e1308064417309-224x300.jpg"><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.chrisstevens.us/images/mooney-prop-vertical-e1308064417309-224x300.jpg" title="[Mooney]" ></a></p>

<p>As I mentioned in <a href="http://chrisstevens.us/2011/06/its-annual-maintenance-time-again/">this post</a> last week, we started the required annual inspection on our Mooney today.  This post covers the first few days of a typical inspection like this.</p>

<h4>Step 1: Get the airplane to the shop.</h4>

<p>This should be easy, especially since our awesome mechanic is at our home airport.  When I get to the hanger, the battery is not just dead, but completely and very pitifully dead.   Even the cockpit lights struggle to wake up from a deep slumber.  This is one of the big reasons that I try to fly every 10-14 days.  Your car runs almost every day and the engine and electrical systems receive almost constant exercise.  Airplanes (and their pilots) should be so lucky!</p>

<h4>Step 2: Take off a bunch of very hot panels.</h4>

<p>After fetching a fresh battery from the shop, it&rsquo;s time to actually get started.  I drive around the airport for about 10 minutes to get the engine warmed up and then head over to the shop.  We remove the engine cowling and start draining the oil.  Airplane engines are air cooled, so without the normal 150 mph airflow, those metal panels and screws were nice and toasty.</p>

<p>I typically hang around for a few hours after dropping off to look over the naked engine and prop and to help remove some of the 30+ inspection panels.  Removing panels on a Mooney can take from 1-3 hours depending on the stubbornness of the 10+ screws per panel that have had at least the past year to work themselves in tightly.  That&rsquo;s me on my back on the floor for 1-3 hours, but it&rsquo;s definitely therapeutic for a mechanical engineer that spends 10 or more hours a day in front of a computer.  The mechanic and I also share some choice words for the 1960s-era engineers down in Kerrville that left us so very little room to do anything inside the airframe.  Thanks alot, fellas.</p>

<h4>Step 3: Get out of Tom&rsquo;s Way.</h4>

<p>That&rsquo;s about the extent of my involvement in the process.  The key is really to get out of Tom&rsquo;s way (our mechanic).  While I was collecting grease with my face under the belly of the airplane, he&rsquo;s already well into his &ldquo;zone&rdquo; working around the engine compartment:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>compression and structural checks on each cylinder (roughly indicative of their health and remaining lifespan)</p></li>
<li><p>inspect the spark plugs, plug wires, magnetos, battery (hey, we have a new one now &ndash; that&rsquo;ll be $300 please)</p></li>
<li><p>inspect the prop, hub, prop governor, carburetor</p></li>
<li><p>inspect the air intact and exhaust systems</p></li>
<li><p>inspect the vacuum pump, standby vacuum system, firewall</p></li>
<li><p>about 100 other things all called out in the official Maintenance Manual for our specific Mooney make and model</p></li>
</ul>


<h4>What&rsquo;s Next?</h4>

<p>Tom will spend the next few days looking at engine, airframe, landing gear, instrumentation, flight controls, and the rest of the Maintenance Manual.  After that is a bunch of paperwork, engine and systems testing and sign-off, and a quick test flight by yours truly.  More on those items next time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How much does an airplane cost anyway?]]></title>
    <link href="http://chrisstevens.us/blog/2011/06/09/how-much-does-an-airplane-cost-anyway/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-09T17:32:48-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://chrisstevens.us/blog/2011/06/09/how-much-does-an-airplane-cost-anyway</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.chrisstevens.us/images/mooney_logo_tag.jpg"><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.chrisstevens.us/images/mooney_logo_tag-300x231.jpg" title="[Mooney Logo]" ></a></p>

<p>Most people I talk to don&rsquo;t know much about general aviation.  The closest I usually get is that somebody&rsquo;s dad was a pilot or airline pilot or they rode in a &ldquo;cessna&rdquo; once (yup, that&rsquo;s a lowercase &ldquo;c&rdquo; as if it encompassed an entire genre of vehicles).  It&rsquo;s a mysterious topic to most people, so I always try to relate it to something a little more mainstream, like cars.</p>

<p>Being the Statesman that I am, I&rsquo;m not going to lie to you.  Airplanes are expensive, like house or boat or Aston Martin expensive.  But! That&rsquo;s not to say there isn&rsquo;t some wiggle room. The older and less capable you go, the more affordable plane you can get into.  Most of us mere mortals will only ever be able to eek into a &ldquo;well-loved&rdquo; older model of flying machine, if at all, and that&rsquo;s more than adequate.</p>

<p>How about some numbers from the &ldquo;mere mortal&rdquo; class, but you&rsquo;ll have to reach back about 30 or 40 years&hellip;</p>

<p>1960-1970 Cessna 172:  $30,000 &ndash; $50,000
1960-1970 Mooney:  $35,000 &ndash; $75,000 (we have a 1965 Mooney)</p>

<p>Now if we move up to something really nifty and new (made in the last decade)&hellip;</p>

<p>2006 Cessna 172S:  $199,000
2005 Mooney Ovation 2: $300,000
2005 Cirrus SR-22 GTS: $270,000</p>

<p>I typically like to say that a &ldquo;well-loved&rdquo; airplane is roughly equivalent in purchase price to a sports or luxury car:</p>

<p>2008 BMW 6-Series 650i: $53,000 (Ebay motors)
2008 Z06 Corvette: $59,000 (Ebay motors)</p>

<p>Of course, the purchase price is only one of the costs of aircraft ownership and it can often be mortgaged out to 15 or 20 years.  You probably already have a place to park your cars, but you&rsquo;ll need a hanger or tie down on an airport.  Inner-city airport parking typically comes with a premium just like anything else in the city (it is valuable real estate, after all). We are fortunate to have a great little airport just outside of the city that is easy to get to and from during the crazy DFW rush hour.</p>

<p>Beyond those big items, you&rsquo;ll have other fixed costs like maintenance, training, and insurance; charts and database subscriptions so you know where you are and how to get home; electricity for the hanger if want lights at night. (We don&rsquo;t have lights at night.)</p>

<p>Often, it is the prospect of paying all of these fixed costs that really gets people interested in shared ownership.  There is a lot to like about shared ownership and we may try that someday.</p>

<p>In the next post, I&rsquo;ll talk about our ownership experience here in the DFW Metroplex and a few of our typical trips.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[It's Annual Maintenance Time Again]]></title>
    <link href="http://chrisstevens.us/blog/2011/06/03/its-annual-maintenance-time-again/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-03T10:33:21-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://chrisstevens.us/blog/2011/06/03/its-annual-maintenance-time-again</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.chrisstevens.us/images/mooney-annual-2010.jpg"><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.chrisstevens.us/images/mooney-annual-2010.jpg" title="[Mooney Annual Maintenance]" ></a></p>

<p>Each year, aircraft owners enjoy at least a week of downtime for FAA-mandated &ldquo;annual&rdquo; maintenance.  People often ask me how I feel about flying a machine built in 1965.  I typically respond with something like: Imagine if we took your car apart once a year, looked into the engine, analyzed the oil for contaminants and metallics, and applied a list of manufacturer required maintenance and safety items from the previous year.  You would see cars that last longer, perform better, and are safer.  By that same token, the design lifespan for cars is short enough to almost negate this level of attention.</p>

<p>We had a bit of concern leading up to our first annual in 2010 since the previous owner had owned the aircraft since 1979.  There is no way to really know what a fresh set of eyes will turn up even though we had a very experience Mooney shop perform the pre-purchase inspection.  Those pre-purchase inspections aren&rsquo;t required by any regulation, but I can&rsquo;t imagine making a big purchase without one.</p>

<p>Our 2010 annual turned out just fine.  I helped do some of the easier chores like removing panels, landing gear doors, etc.  All this helped our mechanic (Tom) get through the process 1-2 days sooner.  Probably more importantly, I had a chance to look in, over, and around many deep and dark places originally assembled more than 46 years ago in Kerrville, Texas.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll have some new pictures and more details about the process as our 2011 inspection kicks off in a few weeks.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
