<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ForeFlight | Chris Stevens]]></title>
  <link href="http://chrisstevens.us/blog/categories/foreflight/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://chrisstevens.us/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-31T10:04:53-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://chrisstevens.us/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Chris Stevens]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flying Digital: iPad + ForeFlight HD (Part 2)]]></title>
    <link href="http://chrisstevens.us/blog/2011/04/06/flying-digital-ipad-foreflight-hd-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-06T07:35:51-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://chrisstevens.us/blog/2011/04/06/flying-digital-ipad-foreflight-hd-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.chrisstevens.us/images/dfw-enroute-chart-e1302109024961.png"><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.chrisstevens.us/images/dfw-enroute-chart-e1302109024961.png" title="[DFW Enroute Chart]" ></a></p>

<p>In <a href="http://chrisstevens.us/2011/04/04/flying-digital-ipad-foreflight-hd/">Part 1</a>, I talked about the benefits of going paperless in the cockpit with the iPad.  For this installment, I&rsquo;ll go over some actual early in-flight operations.  Mounting options, flight control clearance, and screen polarization are covered.</p>

<p>Both flights so far (1 IFR and 1 VFR) were performed with only the trial period of the Foreflight HD software.  That means that you can&rsquo;t bulk download charts and data for a whole region.  You have to lookup each airport and save all of the terminal plates and then scroll around the map area that you&rsquo;ll need.  Also, the &ldquo;Pro&rdquo; subscription is required to test the geo-referenced approach and taxi charts.  It would have been nice to be able to try this during my 30-day trial period, but it is a new feature and I hope it will be added to the trial at a later date.</p>

<p>Discarding the IFR flight because I hadn&rsquo;t read the software user manual yet leaves us with a bumpy local VFR flight.  Mooney cockpits are notoriously compact like a sports car, so the first issue is finding space for the iPad.  The instrument panel is full and the Johnson bar for the manual landing gear leaves out a lower-pedestal mounting option, so I&rsquo;m left with the kneeboard option.  This is fine anyway since I almost always fly with a kneeboard and there are some swanky new boards coming to market especially for the iPad.  The other issue with the kneeboard is that the flight control arm comes dangerously close to the iPad glass nearing full right deflection.  It&rsquo;s rare that we need full right deflection, but if we did, it&rsquo;s highly unlikely that I&rsquo;ll have enough time to ensure that the pretty glass is safely clear before righting the aircraft.  I don&rsquo;t think Cessna drivers will have this problem, and certainly the side-stick (Cirrus and Lancair) guys are loving all their knee-room.</p>

<p>My next issue is polarization of the screen.  With my now 4-year old Maui Jim&rsquo;s, the iPad screen is completely black in portrait mode.  Rotate to landscape and all is great in the world except my space issue with the flight controls.  Also, the approach charts are portrait and look glorious that way.  If you wear (and like) polarized sunglasses, you&rsquo;ll want to check this out before purchase and preferrably in sunlight.</p>

<p>In the next installment, we&rsquo;ll cover building and actually flying routes.  There is at least one trick that you&rsquo;ll need to know before launching out into a real flight.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flying Digital: iPad + ForeFlight HD (Part 1)]]></title>
    <link href="http://chrisstevens.us/blog/2011/04/04/flying-digital-ipad-foreflight-hd/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-04T09:02:08-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://chrisstevens.us/blog/2011/04/04/flying-digital-ipad-foreflight-hd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.chrisstevens.us/images/foreflight-ipad.jpg"><img src="https://s3.amazonaws.com/static.chrisstevens.us/images/foreflight-ipad.jpg" title="[ForeFlight on iPad]" ></a></p>

<p>One of the on-going expenses in operating an aircraft is buying both VFR and IFR charts and publications every 1-2 months.  These aren&rsquo;t normally expensive either, typically about $8 per region, but our usual intra-Texas flights require 6 different publications.  Imagine then traveling across several states (our trip to Florida required 10 pubs) or the farther.</p>

<p>When the original iPad first launched, the aviation community saw some immediate parallels to the existing state-of-the-art electronic flight bags of the time.  Those devices, both highly specialized and ruggedized for the rigors of cockpit life, sold for thousands of dollars and had just one mission in life.  The iPad can do all that and much more with the right software.</p>

<p>After passing on the first-gen iPad, I picked up a shiny new iPad 2 on launch day with a plan to use it while flying in addition to the daily web consumption activities.  I&rsquo;ll have to tell the iPad2 launch day store later.</p>

<p>I almost immediately loaded a free trial of arguably the best in-flight software for the iPad: <a href="http://www.foreflight.com/ipad">ForeFlight HD</a>.  The maps and charts are gorgeous and bright and full color, whereas the printed publications come in any color you like as long as you like black.</p>

<p>The mid-size iPad or bigger can hold all of the charts, maps, and publications for the whole US.  Weight and volume are a big deal in light aircraft transportation and this device and appropriate software can replace an entire case of paper for cross country flight.</p>

<p>One of the big issues in a transition to digital is safety of flight.  Paper is pretty safe and not known to spontaneous combustion, so short of being tossed out a window, most pilots are usually confident that their paper charts will be available when needed.  With digital devices, people start to worry about failures, blue screens of &ldquo;death&rdquo;, backups, and the regulations.  I&rsquo;m not completely convinced yet, but I&rsquo;m headed down the path.</p>

<p>I also think the pricing model for the Foreflight software is pure genius.  With my annual subscription fee, which is far, far less than buying a year worth of paper charts, I can use the software on 1 iPad <em>and</em> 1 iPhone!  Woohoo!  Now, I have a digital backup for the main device and still don&rsquo;t need any paper.</p>

<p>In the next installment, I&rsquo;ll talk about my flight tests with the new system.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
